<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to a gentleman elected a knight of the shire to serve in the present Parliament</title>
            <author>Wagstaffe, Thomas, 1645-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65984</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1640</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12368974</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12368974</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60500</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65984)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60500)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 903:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to a gentleman elected a knight of the shire to serve in the present Parliament</title>
                  <author>Wagstaffe, Thomas, 1645-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Wagstaffe. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Officials and employees --  Selection and appointment.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60500:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Letter to a <hi>Gentleman</hi> elected a Knight of the Shire to ſerve in the <hi>preſent Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen you were choſe by the Majority of the Freeholders for the Counts of— you were pleaſed to expreſs your ſelf on that Occaſion. That though you were very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>e of the Kindneſs of the Country in pitching on you to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them; yet, at the ſame time, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> great Burthen laid upon your Shoulders; a mighty Truſt repoſed in you; and which required the utmoſt Care and Vigilance to diſcharge faithfully. For that the Nation was in ſuch a Poſture, and the Matters that would come before you were like to be of ſuch extraordinary Weight and Moment, That all the Powers and Vertues of a Man, The greateſt Prudence, The moſt upright Sincerity, and the ſteddieſt Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, were little enough to grapple with, though all the Members were ſingly endow'd with theſe great Qualifications, and which was rather to be wiſhed for than expected, in ſo numerous a Body. Upon the whole, you deſired my Opinion with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>pection <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Conduct and Management in ſo difficult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Juncture, which I ſhall faithfully give you. And I ſhall the more chearfully obey your Commands, becauſe I know you to be a Gentleman of ſuch Qualities, as very well enable you to ſerve your Country, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly at this time. For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, you are a True <hi>Engliſh man,</hi> who always have, and, I doubt not, always will aim at the Welfare of your Country, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from all Parties of all Denominations. The Intereſt of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is an intire Thing, and ſubſiſts of it ſelf; it ſupports all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but is of none of them; 'tis neither a Courtier, nor a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-man: the <hi>Publick</hi> is the Whole and can therefore be of no Side, nor Faction. The late Parliament hath furniſhed us with a Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction between the <hi>Court</hi> and the <hi>Country</hi> Party, the <hi>Church</hi> and the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> Party: But if there be not a third Party independent of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ther, the Whole is like to be torn to pieces by particular
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60500:2"/> and factious Intereſts: So that whatever Party a Man may be of in his private Judgment, he ought to be of none in his <hi>Repreſentative Capacity,</hi> which is, contrary to all diſtinction and partiality, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſts him with the ſame publick and common Relation to the whole Body. I will not preſage of the Temper of your Houſe; but this I will venture to ſay, That if any Man comes there, with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Biaſs beſides that of the Publick Good, he is a thouſand times fitter to ſit as a Delegate from Thieves and Pick-pockets, than to repreſent the Free-born People of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, your Honeſty is inflexible, not to be bended with Frowns or Favours; you will not be threatned nor cajol'd to act againſt your Judgment, or to decline it by ſilence or abſence, when it is fit to declare it, much leſs will you be warp'd by <hi>Bribes,</hi> or any thing equivalent to Bribes. I know you never took the Houſe of Commons for a <hi>Shop</hi> to ſell <hi>Votes</hi> in; your Eſtate is above it, and your Conſcience abhors it. There is nothing more free than a Houſe of Commons; but if the Perſons ſhall ſuffer themſelves to be frighted, tempted, or bought, there is nothing in Nature more Slaviſh; ſuch mercenary Tools are not Repreſentatives: For whatſoever Formality paſſes at the Election, the Writ inſtead of a Member returns only a <hi>Broaker,</hi> or a <hi>Chap man,</hi> who firſt ſells his own Liberty, and then that of the People.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, your Judgment is ſound, clear and peircing, able to dive into the Depths of Buſineſs; to unr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>el the Webs of Cunning and Artifice; to ſee through the Miſts and Obſcurities raiſed by a contriving Party, to clog and hamper the beſt Deſigns. Wiſdom is as neceſſary in a Senator as Honeſty. Tricks cannot paſs upon a Man who hath a due preſence of Mind, and a ſteddy Judgment: And he will perſue a good Cauſe through all the Mazes and Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinths, the Embroilments and Intanglements of crafty and winding Interpoſitions and Obſtructions. Nor will he be diverted by Noiſe and Clamour; a Method (however practiſed) more becoming a Mob, or a Tumult, than the Gravity and Wiſdom of an auguſt Senate.</p>
            <p>Theſe, Sir, are Qualities which as I know you are poſſeſſed with, ſo do they very well ſuit with your preſent Character, and enable you to become a very uſeful Member of that honourable Aſſembly. A compleat Body, or but a Majority, of ſuch Men would revive our drooping Spirits; and we might yet hope to ſee the Kingdom ſet to Rights, the Ancient Glory of <hi>England</hi> retrieved, and the <hi>great matters</hi> to come before you adjuſted, to the Advantage and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the whole Nation.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60500:2"/>
            <p>And which I ſhall now more particularly apply my ſelf to, and for Methods ſake ſhall ſpeak to them under ſeveral and diſtinct Branches.</p>
            <p>In the firſt Place, there is no doubt but the great Buſineſs of <hi>Money,</hi> and <hi>Supply,</hi> will be the main ſubject of the King's Speech, and with all Care recommended to the Conſideration of the <hi>Houſe of Commons;</hi> and for this, you muſt expect to be often called upon and reminded by the <hi>Court,</hi> if you do not go faſt enough of your ſelves. This indeed is a weighty Point, one of the <hi>Ardua Regni,</hi> and more ſo now than ever; and therefore deſerves your beſt Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon many Accounts, I ſhall ſuggeſt to you theſe following.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That whatever Supplies you think reaſonable to Grant to the Government, that it be done in ſuch <hi>Order,</hi> that thereby the other neceſſary Affairs of the Kingdom be not prejudiced, or wholy neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected. I need not direct to a Method for managing this; Beſides the plain reaſon of things, you have Preſidents in all Ages; the Wiſdom of our Anceſtors, and even of Parliaments within our own Memory, have always thought it highly requiſite to Poſtpone the <hi>Supplies</hi> to the Redreſs of <hi>Grievances;</hi> that however Liberal they have been to our Monarchs, they ever took Care in the firſt Place to ſecure the Rights of the People at home. And the Reaſon of this is obvious, and undeniable; for Parliaments ſitting purely at the Will of the King, when once the Ends of the Government are anſwered, there is no further need of you; and it is no Prophecy to tell you, That ſo ſoon as you have done with the <hi>Money Bill,</hi> the Court hath done with you for this time, and you ſhall be ſent into the Country with the beſt part of your Buſineſs undone. You have freſh Inſtances and Experiences of this; our Grievances have been brought into the Houſe, and debated ſometimes warmly enough by our worthy Patriots, but the Debates have always proved abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and they left our Grievances juſt where they found them: And for this Reaſon, and for this only, for that they had <hi>firſt</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected the <hi>Supplies.</hi> What therefore I here recommend to you is nor an Oppoſition between the <hi>Supplies</hi> and <hi>Grievances,</hi> but only matter of <hi>Method,</hi> and <hi>Order<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and ſurely it will not need much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, in what Place to lay that, which either muſt be firſt done, or not done at all. You have but one Seaſon for this, and that is to <hi>begin</hi> with the <hi>Grievances;</hi> which if you neglect, 'tis, like time it ſelf, irrecoverable, and will never more return this Seſſion. And give me leave plainly to tell you, That if you diſpatch the Supplies, and then <hi>afterwards</hi> fall upon the Grievances, 'tis only to amu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60500:3"/> the People, and to ſtop their Mouths; but this Covering is already worn ſo thin that every Man ſees through it: For 'tis the moſt viſible Deluſion to pretend to be earneſt to do a Thing, and at the ſame time to pretermit the only Opportunity in which it can be done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The great Poverty, and low Eſtate of the Nation, is that which every <hi>Engliſhman</hi> ſees, and <hi>feels</hi> too; (except thoſe only who have fill'd their Pockets at the Kingdoms Coſt) The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Loſſes at Sea, the utter decay of Trade, the exceſſive and conſtant Taxes, have drain'd the Kingdom to the very Bones, and this ſure deſerves to be one Conſideration, when the Caſe of the Money comes before you. 'Tis not the Superfluities and Luxury, the Pride and Wantonneſs of a People, that is to be the Matter of theſe Supplies; but our Bread, and our Drink, the Neceſſities and Supports of Life: Whatſoever you now give is drawn from the Quick, and is juſt ſo much paid from the Subſiſtence of our Families. And ſurely there needs no Argument to perſwade our Repreſentatives, when they come to give our Money, to take their Meaſures from the <hi>Poverty</hi> of the People; and to conſider what they can give, as well as what is asked. Six or Seven Millions for one Year, would have been thought an intolerable Burthen in the moſt flouriſhing and proſperous Condition this Nation ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd: But when we have born that Year after Year, beſides the additional Impoveriſhment of unſpeakable Loſſes, to repeat the ſame, or to advance upon us, is to confound all the Diſtinction of Things; to make no difference between Proſperity and Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity; to lay the ſame Load on a Man languiſhing with Age and Infirmity, as upon the Healthful, Vigorous, and Luſty. In ſhort, Our Veins are emptied already, and you have now our Hearts Blood in your Hands, and which certainly ought to be ſqueez'd gently, that it may preſerve, and not utterly exhauſt, the poor Remnant of Life that is yet left. I ſhall not undertake to determine what Proportion is fit for you to Grant, only I conceive in that Caſe the following Conſiderations on this Head may be uſeful.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A ſtrict and impartial Enquiry what Proportion our Expences bear to the reſt of the Confederates: And if it be found to exceed, to reduce it to equal Bounds. For 'tis the moſt unreaſonable Thing in the World, when the War is primarily and principally theirs, and at their own Doors, that we muſt bear three Parts of the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. If any Party muſt over-pay, that ſurely ought to be the Part of thoſe whoſe Intereſts and Effects lie immediately at Stake, Had we never ſo much Plenty and Abundance, ſuch a manner of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60500:3"/> Proceeding might make us perhaps very kind Neighbors, but no very wiſe Men. And, in good truth, our Conduct in this War is laught at all over <hi>Europe,</hi> and we are become a Scorn and Reproach, even to thoſe who reap the Benefit of our Folly. The Concern of our Allies in this War is ten times more than ours; 'tis flaming within their Bowels, or at their Frontiers. Their Country and Intereſts are defended; and if there be any thing gained by the War, 'tis theirs altogether: We neither have, nor have any Expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to get any thing but <hi>Blows.</hi> And yet (to the Honour of our Diſcretion be it ſpoken) we pay two Thirds at leaſt of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence. Let us aſſiſt our Allies, but then let us do it by the Rules of Equity and Prudence: Their Account in the War is Immediate, and Direct, ours only Remote and Collateral. And it is the moſt unaccountable Thing in the World, That, in ſuch a Caſe, we muſt drein our Men, and our Money, and reduce our ſelves to Beggary, only to ſave their Pockets, and that they may ſit eaſy and flouriſh by our Miſeries. For 'tis as plain as the Sun, That the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of our Quota is a Diminution of theirs; and we pay the <hi>more,</hi> that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> may pay the <hi>leſs.</hi> And it is no wonder, That, by ſuch an unequal Diſtribution, they thrive and grow Rich under a War that is within them, and at their very, Doors, while we at a Diſtance, and upon the moſt advantageous Circumſtances, are notwithſtanding impoveriſhed to the laſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. Do we believe that if we were attaqued at home, our Neighbors would, ſend us a double Supply of Men and Money, and take upon them two Shares of the War; and not rather think they uſed us well, if they gave the Aſſiſtance of a Sixth, or even a Tenth part? We have a freſh and flagrant Inſtance to guide as in making a right Judgment, and even to teach us Wiſdom (if we will learn it) by the Practice of our Neighbours. At this very time <hi>Namur,</hi> and its Dependencies is engaged to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and actually in their hands, to defray their Expencies of the War, and of its Repairs: And yet it is a <hi>Barrier</hi> to their Country, and in that reſpect they would have the ſame account in it, as well in the Hands of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> as in their own. But for all that, they thought it Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to take good Security even of their Allies for Reimburſment. They are wiſe Men, and good Husbands, and underſtand Things better than to think the Name of <hi>Ally</hi> means a <hi>Fool,</hi> to fright and pay all for the Benefit of others, without taking ſome Share of it to themſelves. But what, I pray, have we got? We ſight for the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60500:4"/> 
               <hi>Spaniard</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> too, and yet we have no Mortgages, nor Cautionary Towns; nor ſo much as a poor Hoſpital for our Sick and Wounded. Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> aſſiſted the <hi>Dutch,</hi> not when they were Great and Rich as now, but when they were as Low and Poor as our ſelves are, and yet ſhe thought good to take <hi>Cautionary Towns</hi> of them, although ſhe was at the ſame time actually engaged with their Enemy in the ſame War. But we are grown of late mighty Generous; we fight and pay <hi>Gratis.</hi> 'Tis enough for us to have Honour for our Blood and Money, let the Spoils go to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary; and, in truth, our part in the War hath hitherto been nothing elſe but <hi>Knight-Errantry.</hi> We have rigg'd out <hi>Fleets,</hi> and ſent out <hi>Armies,</hi> in queſt of Adventures, and to relieve <hi>diſtreſſed Ladies;</hi> but never had the leaſt thought of having any profitable return of our Arms, or making any Proviſion for our ſelves. And however this might paſs in heat of Blood, and when our Coffers were full and ran over; yet ſure 'tis now high time to take Example by our Neighbors, and to have ſome Caution and Security for all the vaſt Expence of Men and Treaſure we have been at on their Account; or at leaſt to ſettle Things on ſuch a Foundation, That our <hi>Allies,</hi> who have ten times the Intereſt in the War, ſhould at leaſt bear an equal Share in the Expence: And for this you have a very good Preſident before you in a <hi>Vote</hi> of the laſt Parliament, <hi>April</hi> 18. <hi>That this Kingdom be put upon an equal Foot and Proportion with the reſt of the Allies in bearing the Charge of the preſent War:</hi> Which Vote ought to be revived, and inſiſted on: And it is of ſuch great Importance, and of ſo much Advantage to the Nation, that if it be effectually purſued, I dare promiſe you, it will ſave the Kingdom near one half of this Years Expences.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A <hi>General Exciſe</hi> likewiſe will require your Thoughts; not that I think it will ever be brought into your <hi>Houſe</hi> by any True <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhman:</hi> But it is ſo generally diſcourſed of as a Project to raiſe Money, that it will highly deſerve your Conſideration. And it is true, it will certainly raiſe Money, ſo long as there is any in the Nation to be raiſed: But I hope that is not <hi>All</hi> that is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered by an <hi>Engliſh Parliament,</hi> The Eaſe, Safety, and Freedom of the People, equally deſerves your Care, and eſpecially when you are giving away their Money. And what then will become of the ſo much boaſted of <hi>Engliſh Liberty,</hi> when <hi>Slavery</hi> ſhall be laid on us with both hands, and we ſhall be ſunk into the utmoſt Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips of the Subjects of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Commonwealth: <hi>Engliſh Liberty</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:60500:4"/> means the Liberty of the <hi>People:</hi> And if this load be once laid on us, there will be nothing left but the Name, and we ſhall not in reality enjoy any one Privilege above our Neighbors. Our Gentry will be as much curb'd, our Farmers oppreſſed, and our Peaſants as poor as in any other Nation. For conſider how many are there of the loweſt Rank of the People, who now under the general decay o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Trade, and dearneſs of all Commodities, with all their Labour and Induſtry, cannot ſupport themſelves and Families? And what will their Caſe then be, when every thing they Eat and Drink, and are Cloathed with, and Uſe, muſt over and above pay a Tax to the Government? So that this is a Tax that will eat into the very Hearts of the Poor, and make their Condition deſperate; and, in truth, will ultimately redound upon the <hi>Rich.</hi> For it muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity multiply the Poor, and conſequently the Charges of every Pariſh, and will thereby prove a double Tax to the Rich: Firſt to pay their own Exciſe, and then to maintain them who are beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar'd by it. Beſides, it reflects Hardſhip upon all other States in the Nation; upon another, and indeed a more ſtinging Accounts, it ſubjects them to the Inſolence and Saucineſs of every pitiful <hi>Exciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> who ſhall enter and ſearch their Houſes when, and as often as he pleaſes; and they can neither keep themſelves, their Families, nor any thing they have, <hi>private</hi> from every officious and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering Raſcal. But beſides theſe (which are bad enough) there are yet two other terrible Conſequences that attend a <hi>General Exciſe;</hi> the one is, That it infinitely multiplies abſolute Dependencies on the Crown: The Officers of all Sorts in their ſeveral Diſtricts all over the Kingdom will amount to many Thouſands; and if it was thought to deſerve Complaint, that there were ſo many Officers in your <hi>Houſe,</hi> what will it do when there are ſo many Thouſands throughout the Nation? This, in the firſt place, will have a bad Influence on all Elections of Members of Parliament; for all <hi>their</hi> Votes, in every County in <hi>England,</hi> will certainly be determined at the Will of the Court: And I need not ſay what a dreadful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect this hath on that Fundamental Right of the <hi>Engliſh Nation, viz. Freedom</hi> of chuſing their Repreſentatives. And the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their <hi>Numbers</hi> is full out as formidable, that their united Strength may be able to endanger the Nation to keep it under, and to rule it by a ſtrong hand. 'Tis a kind of <hi>ſtanding Army,</hi> and which may be imployed to other Purpoſes, beſides collecting Exciſe, whenſoever opportunity offers. And it hath ever been the Wiſdom
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60500:5"/> as well as the Jealouſy of <hi>Engliſh Parliaments</hi> never to intruſt the Prince with ſo much Power as to enable him to govern Arbitrarily whenſoever he pleaſes. And which a <hi>General Exciſe</hi> does alſo upon another Account, it lays in an <hi>eternal Fund</hi> for Supplies, which will anſwer all the Ends of the Government, and utterly takes off all the Need the Prince may have of the Peoples Aſſiſtance, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently roots up the very Foundation of Parliaments, and makes them perfectly uſeleſs: So that, at one Blow, this Tax deſtroys all the Rights and Freedom of the Nation. I know to obviate this it may be ſaid, That the <hi>Exciſe</hi> may be laid to hold for a determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate time, and no longer, or during the War only: But this is no anſwer to any Man that can ſee but three Inches before him. For the King is left in Poſſeſſion, and who ſhall diſpute it with him, if he reſolves to have it Collected, eſpecially being backt by a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Troop of Officers, whoſe Subſiſtence and Livelihood depends upon it? A Parliament may diſpute it indeed, but then we may have none, or only ſuch a one that ſhall be compoſed of <hi>Exciſe-men,</hi> whoſe Intereſt it will be to continue it from Generation to Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Methinks in this point we may take warning from our Neighbors the <hi>Dutch;</hi> they began it in the Exigencies of their State, but have continued, it through all their Flouriſhing and Proſperity, and no doubt will never eaſe the People of it to the end of the World.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Seeing we are upon the Article of <hi>Money,</hi> it may not be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to pretermit the State of the <hi>Coin</hi> it ſelf: I do not mean here only as it is <hi>Embaſed</hi> and <hi>Clipt,</hi> (for which in a great meaſure we are beholding to our good Neighbors, who have expreſſed their Gratitude to us in this Inſtance, as well as many others.) And the <hi>Gold</hi> which is not clipt, the current Price is Uncertain and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary, though it be advanced above the Standard of all <hi>Europe;</hi> and the baſeneſs of our <hi>Silver,</hi> and, the <hi>height</hi> and even <hi>uncertainty</hi> of our <hi>Gold,</hi> have a mighty Influence on all Parts of Trade, but more particularly on all Foreign Trade; upon the Account of which the <hi>Exchange</hi> is ſunk, and there is 20 <hi>l.</hi> if not 30 <hi>l. per Cent.</hi> difference, in all the Commodities the <hi>Engliſh</hi> buy or ſell, to what it was heretofore; and which therefore, and upon many other Accounts, will deſerve your Care to apply ſome effectual Remedy. But that which I principally aim at, and is indeed proper upon this Head, is the <hi>Scarcity</hi> even of that Coin, which is thus nought either in kind or degree. We have ſcarcely bad Coin enough left to ſupply
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60500:5"/> the abſolute Neceſſities of Trade, and of Private Families. And I was going to ſay, that when you are granting our Mony: This is a conſideration, that muſt be thought upon, whether you will, or no; for if you do not find <hi>Mony</hi> as well as <hi>Votes,</hi> you may give as you Will, and neither the Government nor our Allies will be much the better for it. And therefore it ſeems ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary, as well with reſpect to the Government as to the People throughly to conſider both the nature and quality of our preſent Coin, and alſo what proportion of it there is yet left among us; for if the King wants it <hi>Abroad,</hi> and the Neceſſities of the People cannot ſpare it <hi>from Home,</hi> 'tis plain, one of them muſt be great ſufferers: For I ſhall take theſe two things for granted; Firſt, That the Nation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not drive a Trade, nor yet ſubſiſt with <hi>Copper Farthings or Halfpence.</hi> Secondly, That the <hi>Exportation</hi> of our Coin, hath been the only reaſon of that great ſcarcity that is now in the Kingdom. And if it be ſuffered to continue, it is impoſſible but it muſt drain away all that remains, for our Mony is embas'd and clipt to half the value, and conſequently the Exportation muſt be double to what it was formerly, one Million of our Mony tranſmitted <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> will prove but half ſo much in the Expence Abroad, for tho' we take it by Tale, and according to the Stamp, yet Foreigners will take it only by weight, and according to the intrinſick value; ſo that if two Millions were Exported yearly to <hi>Flanders,</hi> to the Allies, and to the <hi>Streights,</hi> now for the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, muſt be Exported four Millions, and then let any Man judge what will be left at home, for the ſubſiſtence of the Nation. The King himſelf was ſo ſenſible of this, that (when the Kingdom was in a better Condition then it is now;) He tells the laſt Parliament in his Speech, That He could heartily wiſh ſome Expedient might be found to prevent the Exportation of our Mony. And ſuch an <hi>Expedient</hi> I ſhall now lay before you, and which is liable to no manner of Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but will anſwer all the Ends of the Government, and alſo ſecure the remaining Bullion to ſupply the Neceſſities of the People. And it is this, That we be oblig'd, either with Cloaths ready made, or elſe with Cloath, to Cloath all the Confederate Armies, in <hi>Flanders, Pied<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> and on the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and to furniſh them with Lead, and all Warlike Proviſions of our own growth, or of our conveniency in point of Trade, and to diſcount with our ſeveral Confederates at the ſame rate for theſe Commodities, as they could have provided them in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Countries. This no <hi>Engliſhman</hi> can except againſt, for the manifold advantages it will bring to the Nation. This the <hi>Allies</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60500:6"/> except againſt for Mony worth, and of preſent and neceſſary uſe, is the ſame thing to them with Mony it ſelf, and they may eaſily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the ſubſiſtance of our Troops, when they have a full recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence by an equivalent. I know but of one Objection that can poſſibly be made to this, That it will be more expenſive to the Treaſury, for that ſome of the Commodities may be cheaper in their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, beſides the charge of Exportation. Let this be granted, and poſſibly it may be ſo in ſome meaſure, and there will be ſo much loſt by the diſcount. But this is of no great moment, and will by no means ſerve to ballance theſe mighty Conveniencies that will thereby accrue to the whole Nation, by the Conſumption of our Manufacture, by the reviving our decay'd and almoſt ruin'd Trade, and (which at this time is more than all the reſt) by preventing the Exportation of our Bullion. Suppoſe the Treaſury be a little burthened, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives ſubſiſtence, and all its Supplies from the People, is that a Reaſon to lay aſide an Expedient ſo every way profitable and advantagious to them? And is it not a thouſand times better, that the Treaſury bear a little burden, and which alſo the People muſt pay, than for the ſmall and inconſiderable Eaſe of that, an intolerable and inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table load be laid on the whole People. And in ſhort, the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in its full force is no more but this, the Treaſury muſt not bear the ſupernumerary Expence of five Shilings, tho' by ſo doing the Nation gains five Pounds, and ſaves ten.</p>
            <p>I have now done with the great Point of the <hi>Mony,</hi> and ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to another general Head, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly. There is a ſtrong Report, of a very great, but at the ſame time a very <hi>daring</hi> Project, to endeavour a <hi>new Settlement of the Crown.</hi> This is ſuch a bold attempt on the Conſtitution, that it never durſt be ſet on foot, but by theſe who think the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are grown ſo tame and weak, that they are ſit to be made a Property, and can be prevailed upon to do any thing in the World: What do they think of us? When they can propoſe to us, to put our own hands, to the overturning our Foundations, and breaking through our Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The unſetling the Foundations in any Government, is of that dangerous conſequence, and hath ſuch a train of unforeſeen Miſchiefs attending it, that there is not a Wiſe man upon Earth, that will ever put his hand to it, and I cannot think ſo meanly of your Houſe, that there is one ſingle Member will heartily engage in an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking ſo extreamly raſh, and unadviſed. And (to ſpeak the plain
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60500:6"/> truth, it is a thing you cannot do, tho' you had never ſo much mind to it, for whatever powers a Parliament may have, they are all confin'd within the Terms of the <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> you ſit in Vertue of it, and derive your Powers from it, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you enact in concurrence with it, is valid, and binding, and hath the force of a Law, but whatſoever is in oppoſition to it, or in deſtruction of it, is null and void of it ſelf, and neither obliges your ſelves, nor any body elſe. The utmoſt the <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> pretended (as appears plainly by the Debates and Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between the two Houſes) was a Power to fill a <hi>vacant Throne;</hi> but they utterly diſclaim'd the Power of altering the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and turning an <hi>Hereditary Monarchy</hi> into an <hi>Elective</hi> one: And which <hi>this</hi> apparently does, for what is <hi>ſettled</hi> by Parliament to day, may be <hi>unſettled</hi> by Parliament to morrow, and a new Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made a third day, ſo that we may have not only as many <hi>Monarchs,</hi> but as many <hi>Monarchies</hi> too, as we have Parliaments. And if this be not deſtroying the Foundation, and altering the Conſtitution no man alive knows what is. And therefore before you enter upon this dangerous Point, firſt ask your ſelves theſe Queſtions, How you came to be a <hi>Houſe?</hi> What Authorities you have there? What place you have in the Conſtitution? Whether all your Powers are not purely and ſolely deriv'd from the Conſtitution? And if theſe be effectually anſwer'd, this attempt falls of it ſelf, as being not only beſides the Conſtitution, but in plain contradiction to it, and it is the moſt ridiculous thing in the World to think, that any Body of Men whatſoever can derive an Authority from a Conſtitution in prejudice of it ſelf, much leſs to deſtroy it. Beſides, this will not only deſtroy the Conſtitution, but your ſelves alſo, as Branches of it, and dependant upon it, it will undermin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the very being of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and all your Ancient and Legal Priviledges; for there is ſuch an inſeperable connexion between the Fundamental Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and all the depending Branches of Authority, that they muſt of neceſſity fall together, you cannot derive a Being and Powers from that which is not, and conſequently, whatever elſe you may be, you can be no <hi>Engliſh Parliament,</hi> compos'd of <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> indeed, but not of the <hi>Engliſh Conſtitution.</hi> And this ſure is conſideration ſufficient to make you tender of all Violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Conſtitution and of all ſteps towards it. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Conſtitution, and it will preſerve you, and ſupport
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60500:7"/> you in all your juſt Rights and Priviledges, but if you diſſolve the Conſtitution, you caſhier your ſelves, you will be no longer our old legal Parliament, but muſt ſet up upon a <hi>New</hi> Title, ev'n as new as your <hi>New Settlement;</hi> and you will have but a <hi>Muſhrom</hi> Authority, and but of <hi>yeſterday.</hi> But if your Houſe ſhould be ſo forgetful of it ſelf, and its own Being and Priviledges, is it credible that the <hi>Lords</hi> will lower themſelves, their Honours, and Intereſts which they hold upon the <hi>old Foundation,</hi> they are more nearly related to the Crown, are the <hi>Arms</hi> to uphold and defend it, they derive all their Titles from an <hi>Hereditary Monarchy,</hi> and are more peculiarly oblig'd to ſupport it, not only from the nearneſs they ſtand to it, and immediate dependance they have upon it, but alſo from their particular <hi>Oaths of Homage;</hi> and it is by no means probable, that they will forego all theſe, and whatever you do, there is no likelihood of meeting with any concurrence in that Houſe, which is ſufficient to daſh and diſcourage all ſuch at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, which will only bring <hi>Honour</hi> to the Lords in ſtanding by the Ancient Rights of the Monarchy, and <hi>Shame</hi> to your ſelves in deſerting them.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. There is another flagrant Rumor, of a Deſign to <hi>Alienate</hi> the Revenues of the <hi>Church,</hi> or at leaſt to engage and pawn them for the defraying of great Sums, either of which hath a terrible Aſpect upon the <hi>Church.</hi> And will in the end prove the very ſame. The engaging the Church Lands, as a Fund for Supplies, is the <hi>firſt</hi> ſtept to their Alienation, and the <hi>next</hi> is to aboliſh Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy <hi>Root and Branch,</hi> and then the <hi>Lands</hi> come of courſe, the <hi>Office</hi> will ſoon be found uſeleſs, when the <hi>Revenues</hi> are thought convenient, and the <hi>Inheritance</hi> will endanger the <hi>Heir,</hi> ſo that what was deſign'd by the Piety of Princes, and of Good men, for the Honour, and Security of the Church, will prove the only In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement to deſtroy it, by the Covetous and Rapacious. I ſhall offer you little on this Head, where the Conſequences are ſo apparent; but beware what you do, for you touch <hi>Fire,</hi> which at one time or other will burn your Fingers, for <hi>Sacriledge</hi> never did proſper, nor never will.</p>
            <p>I come to the Fourth and Laſt General Branch, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4thly. The <hi>Grievances,</hi> And here is ſuch a large Field of ſad Matter, that if I ſhould enumerate all Particulars, I ſhould never have done, I ſhall therefore only ſelect ſome <hi>few,</hi> and leave the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60500:7"/> reſt to be ſupplied by your Memory, and ſearch'd into by your Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, beſides the matter of our Grievances, there is ſomewhat of extraordinary Malignity, with reſpect to the <hi>Seaſon,</hi> in which they have been committed, they have not grown upon us through long intervals and diſcontinuance of Parliaments, but have been perpetrated in their very Faces, have throve under the ſhadow of your <hi>Houſe,</hi> and (to ſpeak plain truth) have not only grown under it, but <hi>in</hi> it, and ſome of our moſt Flaming Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances have been born, and bred within the Walls of St. <hi>Stephen's Chappel</hi> it ſelf; and if the Antidote be Poyſon, how great is that Poyſon?</p>
            <p>For <hi>Bribes</hi> of all ſorts, on all Occaſions, and in all Perſons, are of a very black Complexion, but if it affects Perſons of a high Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the greateſt Truſt, and who are oblig'd by all Tyes, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and Divine, to act ſincerely, uprighly, and indifferently, 'tis hideous, and monſtrous, 'tis a crime that wants a name, and uncapable of repreſentation, and it is no wonder it is ſo, for 'tis perfectly <hi>new,</hi> and was never heard of in all the Ages before us. If a Judge, ſells <hi>Judgment,</hi> he deſerves the utmoſt ſeverity that can be inflicted, but if a man in a Legiſlative capacity, ſells a <hi>Law,</hi> 'tis a thouſand times worſe, than <hi>Bribery</hi> in the Adminiſtration, as it corrupts the very Fountains of Juſtice, and poyſons the Springs, that are to convey the Meaſures of Right to the whole Kingdom. The Caſes of the <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Company, and that of the <hi>Orphans</hi> are now notorious to all, as having, in part, been examin'd towards the latter end of the laſt Parliament; and it is undoubtedly your Duty to proceed where they left off, and to purſue it to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom; and for this you have a fair handle, by calling for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Sir <hi>Thomas Cook,</hi> which he delivered in Writing to the Commitee appointed to receive it, and one of that Committee is your preſent <hi>Speaker.</hi> And it is my Motion, and I hope you will ſecond it, that whomſoever you find tampering in theſe lewd Practices, both <hi>Receivers,</hi> and <hi>Givers,</hi> (as being both equally guilty) that you will proceed againſt them with a ſeverity as exemplary, as the Crime is abhominable, that you may for ever put an end to, and baniſh from the Kingdom, the moſt foul and ſcandalous cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in the World.</p>
            <p>But there is another ſort of <hi>Bribes,</hi> tho' called by the finer name of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60500:8"/> 
               <hi>Penſions,</hi> yet equally foul and corrupt, in this they differ indeed, that the <hi>Eaſt-India Penſioner</hi> is <hi>Brib'd</hi> but once, whereas the other receives his <hi>Bribes</hi> all the year, and by annual Allowance; however in this they agree, that the formal Malignity of each, is the ſame, nay, the latter is of the two, the more perfidious and treacherous, and together with his Vote, ſelling his Country, and betraying the greateſt Truſt a People can repoſe in him. Several of theſe were named in particular in the laſt Parliament, how eaſily ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they came off, and if you pleaſe to inſpect the Liſt of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences in the Treaſury, and particularly the prodigious Sums for <hi>Secret</hi> Service, and critically examine into whoſe Pockets that Mony went, I doubt not, you will find many more. However this Matter of <hi>Bribes</hi> (of both kinds) hath alarm'd all the Kingdom, hath reflected diſhonour on your whole Body, and hath weaken'd your Intereſt among the People, inſomuch that it is high time to purge the Infamy of your Houſe, and to take ſome proper and effectual Methods, that ſuch Corruptions be never more heard with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Walls.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. The next thing, I know not what name to call it by, but 'tis a ſtrange and unpreſidented action of ſome of your Members, to indeavour to be choſe for ſeveral places, and particularly <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral Ruſſel</hi> ſtood for <hi>Middleſex,</hi> when he knew he was choſen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and alſo for the County of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and had furthermore declar'd that he would adhere to the choice of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgeſhire,</hi> becauſe his Eſtate lies in that County. This, how ſlight ſoever it may appear at firſt view, is of very great conſequence, not only as it creates diſturbances, and multiplies unneceſſary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences and trouble in new Elections, but (what is infinitely more momentous) as it hath a mighty influence upon the freedom of Parliaments themſelves, for if this Practice be ſuffer'd to paſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Animadverſion, a few popular Men, may ingroſs half the Elections of the Kingdom, and ſo at firſt ſitting down, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament would be only a <hi>Rump,</hi> a partial and incompleat Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the People, and before new Writs could be iſſued out, and return'd, the great Buſineſs of the Nation might be tranſacted by <hi>half</hi> a <hi>Houſe,</hi> and their Mony be given away, and themſelves concluded by Laws, without having any Member of their own to repreſent them, and act in their behalf. And this plainly ſtrikes at the Root of all Parliamentary Proceedings, deludes the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of their Juſt Rights, and if not timely prevented,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60500:8"/> may occaſion more Miſchiefs, than can eaſily be foreſeen.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. And Enquiry into the State of the Navy, and particularly of the <hi>Streights Fleet,</hi> ſeems more eſpecially neceſſary at this time, not only becauſe the furniſhing them with neceſſary Stores and Proviſions at that great diſtance, is treble the Charge to what it would coſt us at home, and at this time of day, 'tis abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to retrench all the Expences we can; not only becauſe a great part of that <hi>Fleet</hi> is diſabled and <hi>honny-comb'd</hi> by the Worm, by the long remaining in thoſe Seas, as plainly all thoſe Great Men of War are, that are come back with Admiral <hi>Ruſſell,</hi> which will require vaſt Sums to repair, and make ſerviceable, and which incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience they were by no means liable to in our own Seas, it need only be remembred, that the ſtrength of <hi>England</hi> conſiſts in her <hi>Wooden Walls,</hi> and if theſe be ſuffer'd to be eaten up, and moulder in the Service of Foreigners, half an eye can ſee, that in the end it muſt prove fatal to the Kingdom. I know 'tis pretended that this Conduct hath broke all the Meaſures of <hi>France,</hi> by dividing their Fleet, and thereby making them unable to offend us, which to me (which ſubmiſſion to wiſer Heads) is one of the ſtrangeſt Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions in the World, for if the Fleet in the <hi>Streights</hi> be too ſtrong for theirs at <hi>Tholoun,</hi> and if ours at home be ſuperiour to theirs at <hi>Breſt,</hi> 'tis little leſs than ridiculous to think that we cannot as eaſily deal with their united Force in our own Seas, and that too without the danger of expoſing our Ships to <hi>Rot,</hi> and the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Expence of maintaining them in another Country. So that, whatever is pretended, 'tis for the Intereſt of <hi>Spain,</hi> and for that only, that our Fleet was ſent, and is ſtill kept there, we our ſelves reap nothing by it, but great Expence, and greater damage to our Ships. But if this ſhall continue year after year, we may ſoon feel the ſmart of this Conduct, and by the conſtant diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling our Men of War, together with the draining of our Mony (the Sinews of War) for their Supply and Repairs, we ſhall be far leſs able to deal with them either at home or abroad: Their Ships lie ſafe, while ours are eternally waſting, and what Tragical Effects this will produce, a very ordinary foreſight may eaſily determine. And I am pretty confident, that if there be not ſpeedily ſome other Meaſures taken, this one thing, as it hath already almoſt broken our backs (as you will ſee preſently) ſo in the end it will prove the utter overthrow and deſtruction of the Kingdom.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60500:9"/>
            <p>But beſides theſe, there is another Matter that earneſtly calls for, your inſpection, and remedy. Admiral <hi>Ruſſell</hi> can tell you if he pleaſe, (and 'tis highly reaſonable that he ſhould be preſs'd home on this Article) how the <hi>Dutch</hi> have been furniſhed with our Stores and Proviſions, without any manner of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count or Payment, how they detach'd their Men of War from the Grand Fleet, to Convoy their Merchants, and carry on the <hi>Levant</hi> Trade, whilſt ours remain'd upon Publick Duty. So that it ſeems, the Terms of Alliance with our Neighbours, are, that we muſt feed them, and fight, while they mind their Buſineſs and their Trade, and gain all the Profits, not only diſtinctly by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but by our Loſſes. And 'tis the ſame in all other branches of Trade, our Fleets are ſtop'd at home by <hi>high hand,</hi> or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe imploy'd, to give them the beſt opportunities, and the Cream of the Markets both for Buying and Selling. Now this perhaps may appear to you as a myſterious Riddle in the Confederacy, that we muſt fight, and pay all, and our Allies gain all; but 'tis unfolded by that powerful and wiſe Maxim, <hi>We muſt oblige the Dutch,</hi> meaning, we muſt give them all the Advantages, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever becomes of our ſelves. And this ſure is a new way to make us a rich and flouriſhing People, to engage us in the greateſt Burthen of the War, and at the ſame time to have our Trade wreſted out of our hands, ev'n by thoſe, for whoſe ſakes we bear it, if therefore you would drive theſe Miſchiefs to their true Spring, and Original, you muſt riſe as high as the <hi>Councils</hi> by which our great Affairs, and particularly thoſe of Trades are manag'd, and it deſerves your enquiry, whether our Allies the <hi>Dutch,</hi> inſtead of minding their own buſineſs, have not too great a ſhare in ours for they have actually got the beſt of our Trade into their hands, and this can proceed but from one of theſe two Cauſes, either from their Management of our Councils, or from our own miſmanagement of them. I muſt confeſs that beloved Maxim, which can never be too often repeated, <hi>We muſt oblige the Dutch,</hi> hath a very kind Aſpect on our Neighbours, although conſidering our preſent vaſt Expence both of Men and Mony on their Account, together with our former Services for that Commonwealth. A poor <hi>Engliſhman</hi> may be ſo fooliſh to think, that the Point of Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is due on the other hand, and the <hi>Dutch ſhould oblige us,</hi> and</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:60500:9"/>4. Theſe unparallel'd, and illegal attempts on the <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the Subject, call aloud to you, not only for remedy for the future, but for puniſhment for the preſent upon the Offenders. The Caſe of <hi>Tooly,</hi> Provoſt Marſhal in <hi>Holborn,</hi> is one of the moſt diſmal and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Stories that ever came before a Parliament; to have <hi>Freemen</hi> kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>napp'd, and ſold like <hi>Slaves,</hi> to be immur'd, and ſtarv'd, and ſuffer'd to dye like <hi>Dogs,</hi> is enough to make every <hi>Engliſhman</hi> to tremble; and that which aggravates it, and adds to our amazement, is the ſlight paſſing it over in the laſt Parliament. When a Complaint was brought into the Houſe againſt Captain <hi>Reyny (Decemb.</hi> 12.) for pretending to hire <hi>Thomas Atkinſon</hi> as a Servant, and then putting him into the Cuſtody of <hi>Tooly.</hi> What became of this? Why truely three days after, in vindication no doubt of the juſt Liberties of the People, Captain <hi>Reyney</hi> was called into the Houſe and <hi>Reprimanded.</hi> A moſt terrible Sentence, and which muſt needs prove a mortal diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hereafter to venture on ſuch villanies, to which there is annex'd the puniſhment of a <hi>Reprimand.</hi> In the mean time, if you do not go thorough with them, and ſtigmatize ſuch Crimes according to their guilt, 'tis much better to let them alone, and leave them wholly to the <hi>Mob</hi> to redreſs; for tho' I am not very fond of a <hi>Mob Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> nor I ſuppoſe is any Perſon elſe, who conſiders it; yet 'tis much better to ſuffer them to take what vengeance they pleaſe, than that ſuch outragious and impudent violations of our Liberty ſhould eſcape unpuniſh'd. And juſt ſuch another Inſtance, but of a yet more tragical nature, is that of the Lord <hi>Conisby</hi> and Sir <hi>Charles Porter,</hi> who hang'd a poor man <hi>(Gaffney)</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> without Tryal, Examination of Witneſſes, or any other Forms of Law, but by the moſt arbitrary Proceedings that ever were heard of; the Fact and all the Circumſtances were undeniably proved before the laſt Parliament, and moreover owned by a Vote of the <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> and yet it was paſs'd over with an excuſe, and the Proſecution ſilenc'd, upon pretence of I know not what <hi>neceſſity</hi> of the Times, and of which neceſſity no man can tell one tittle, or ever heard the reaſon of; for I do not doubt to ſay, that there never was, nor never can be ſuch a <hi>neceſſity</hi> of any State in the World, to hang up a man arbitrarily, in a time and place of peace, when the Courts of Juſtice are open, and by <hi>Civil</hi> Magiſtrates, and not Military, which was apparrent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the caſe in every circumſtance. Now, Sir, I do not know what you will call this, but all the Nation hath hitherto call'd it by the name of <hi>Murder,</hi> and certainly ſo it is, if there be any ſuch thing in the World; and <hi>Murder,</hi> you know is a co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gious Sin, and affects all acceſſories, both before and after th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and whoſoever conſents to it (as he certainly does, who exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> or does not puniſh it, when he is in a Station impowering him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it, is involv'd in the Guilt, equal to the <hi>principal</hi> offender; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:60500:10"/> them who contriv'd, or admitted the excuſe, waſh their hands of it, as well as they can, I am ſure, if you do not take ſome effectual courſe about it, the Guilt will be tranſlated to your doors, and that vengeance which Blood cries for, will be apt to ſtick, not only to your ſelves, but alſo to your innocent Poſterities, for above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sins, this leaves ſuch a taint on the Blood, as will not be purg'd for ſeveral Generations.</p>
            <p>To this Head alſo belongs, the manifold illegal Impriſonments of the Subject, and more eſpecially the hardſhips, ſufferings, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities which have been undergone in Priſon, by thoſe which have been, and by thoſe which have not been offenders againſt the Law, nor ever have been prov'd ſo, nor ſo much as any attempt made to prove it, ev'n to the loſs of the Lives of ſome, the Limbs of others, and the health of many; whereas the whole deſign of Impriſonment, according to the Terms of our <hi>Engliſh Laws,</hi> is only to keep men in ſafe cuſtody, and that they may be forth coming, but hath made all poſſible Proviſion, that Priſoners may not want reaſonable conveniences, and ſupports of life, that they ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer nothing hard, but the meer durance, and much leſs that they ſhould be uſed with the utmoſt inhumanity, and like the Slaves at <hi>Argiers,</hi> ſo that if men are never ſo legally impriſon'd, yet if they are <hi>illegally</hi> us'd, if they are coop'd up into holes, ſtarv'd with cold or want of ſuſtenance, debarr'd of the neceſſary aſſiſtance of their Friends, and Relations, and in fine, if they are treated like Beaſts, by the barbarous and inhumane Keepers, or by order from the Miniſters, the Law is violated, and the <hi>Freedom</hi> of an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> ſacrific'd, let his Crimes be what they will, and which in truth are nothing in the Eye of the Law, till his Tryal and Conviction. If I ſhould deſcend to particulars on this Head, they would fill a Volumn, and therefore I ſhall only repreſent to you a very late and freſh Inſtance. One <hi>Spencely;</hi> (who kept a Coffee-houſe in <hi>Little Wild-ſtreet,</hi>) was taken up, upon a Warrant of <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Priſoner to the Houſe of <hi>Hopkins,</hi> the Meſſenger. He imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately fell ſick of a violent and dangerous Fever, his Wife made ſeveral applications to the Meſſenger, and to the Secretary's Office, but could not get leave to come to the Speech of him, and much leſs to adminiſter to him, and give him that aſſiſtance his condition requir'd; But inſtead of that, Mr. <hi>Ellis</hi> (to whom ſhe apply'd her ſelf at Mr. Secretary <hi>Trumbal</hi>'s Office) revil'd and reproach'd her with hard Language, at length, and when he was paſs'd hopes, ſhe found means, by long and conſtant waiting, to come to the Speech of Mr. Secretary <hi>Trumbal,</hi> (which before ſhe could never do through the behaviour, and power of Mr. <hi>Ellis</hi>) who promis'd her leave, and appointed Mr. <hi>Ellis</hi> to write her an Order to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60500:10"/> but he not only declin'd it, but plainly told her, ſhe could not ſee her Husband, for that Mr. <hi>Aaron Smith</hi> was out of Town. The ſame Evening ſhe attended again, and gave Mr. <hi>Hopkins</hi> a Reward, who took her to Mr. Secretary <hi>Trumball,</hi> and he again gave her liberty, but with this expreſs caution, that ſhe ſhould never be with him her ſelf, nor very long, and which tho Meſſenger pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually executed; whereas his Condition required a <hi>Nurſe,</hi> and not a Viſit. But this is not the worſt of the Caſe, for ſhe procur'd a Friend to write to Sir <hi>Hugh Chamberlain,</hi> and ſtate his Caſe, and deſire his aſſiſtance, both with reſpect to his Faculty, and alſo to his Intereſt at the Secretary's Office, and particularly with Mr. <hi>Ellis.</hi> The Dr. fairly told her, her Husband was paſt recovery, and very kindly went himſelf to the Secretary's Office, and ſpoke to Mr. <hi>Ellis,</hi> that ſome Divine might be admitted to pray with him, and perform the laſt Offices, but Mr. <hi>Ellis</hi> flatly refus'd it, and told him there was too much granted already, and ſo in a few days he died; and in all probability for want of ſeaſonable and fit attendance, and the uſe of proper means for his recovery, to be ſure without that ghoſtly Advice and Council, and Spiritual Adminiſtrations to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare him for another World, which was never before deny'd to the moſt notorious Malefactor, that ever was confin'd to an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſon. This is an action ſo all over barbarous, that it ought not be named amongſt Chriſtian People, Savages and Turks uſe their Priſoners with more Humanity. If it be ſaid that <hi>Spencely</hi> was an <hi>Enemy to the Government,</hi> and ſo deſerv'd no favour nor compaſſion; but the Queſtion is not about <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> but <hi>common Juſtice,</hi> favour to be ſure he had none, but had he <hi>Juſtice</hi> done him? Is it juſt that a ſick man in durance ſhould be admitted to the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Proviſions for his Condition? Then the Priſoner ought to have had them, let him have been what he would, his particular qualities (which I neither meddle with, nor plead for) are quite out of the Queſtion, for if <hi>Juſtice</hi> be any thing, 'tis equal, indifferent, impartial. And if Juſtice once <hi>open her eyes,</hi> and weighs by a falſe ballance, if ſhe can diſcern Parties, and Perſons, and adminiſter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, the Name and the Vertue is gone, 'tis Fraud, Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Partiality, Hypocriſie, or any thing but Juſtice. Moreover no man by the Law, is reputed an Enemy to the Government, till he be <hi>tried</hi> and <hi>convicted,</hi> and if this be the Caſe, what do Laws or Tryals ſignifie? There is a more expeditious way, than by the dull formality of <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Juries,</hi> take him up by a Paper with a Seal to it, and ſend him to the <hi>Goals</hi> or <hi>Meſſengers</hi> to be <hi>Murthered,</hi> and there is an end of him; but withal, there is an end of all Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice too, and no man can be ſafe one moment, for 'tis but clapping a hard name upon your back, and calling you, or ſuſpecting you
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60500:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> for an <hi>Enemy to the Government,</hi> and then away you go to the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibals,</hi> and are never more heard off.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly. <hi>The prodigious Loſſes at Sea,</hi> And theſe I call <hi>Grievances</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Misfortunes, for that they were occaſion'd, by miſcarriage and miſmanagement, if not treachery in the Council. For in the firſt place the Petition of the Merchants for Convoys could not be heard, nor anſwer'd; and Secondly, after the Alarm given, and two <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Ships taken, Admiral <hi>Hobſon</hi> was ſent out with a Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, and who return'd home again, and gave the <hi>French</hi> liberty to take the other three; but that which is the Fundamental miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, is the ſending our Fleet to the <hi>Streights,</hi> to take care of <hi>Spain,</hi> while our own Intereſts are neglected and laid open to the Spoyl, if our Fleet had ſtay'd at home, it is impoſſible that ſuch a Ravage could have been made among the Merchants, our Coaſts would have been guarded, our Seas clear'd, and our Trade open, and unmole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. And here you plainly fee the wonderful poling of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, our Fleet was ſent to the <hi>Streights,</hi> and for this reaſon, becauſe <hi>it broke all the Meaſure of</hi> France, yet their Meaſures muſt needs be broken, becauſe that <hi>thereby</hi> they have gained <hi>five Eaſt-India</hi> Ships, and <hi>five hundred</hi> others, I dare ſay the <hi>French King</hi> would be content to have his Fleet eternally coop'd up at <hi>Thoulon,</hi> if he might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the advantageous opportunities, he has thereby, of enriching himſelf by our Spoyls. Alas, Sir, we are grown the kindeſt People in the World, we will lop off an Arm our ſelves, to ſave the Finger of our Allies, we have ſpent our Men, our Mony, and our Ships too, for the advantage of <hi>Catalonia,</hi> and for that very reaſon, have our ſelves loſt ten times the value of the whole Country. But I need not remind you of this, the whole Kingdom is alarm'd, and all on fire about it, and you cannot but hear of it, and the diſmal Effects of it from all Quarters, and by all ſorts of Perſons.</p>
            <p>I conclude with telling you, that our <hi>Grievances</hi> are the Objects of your Authority and Great Truſt, about which they are to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in order to an effectual Remedy; for if our <hi>Grievances</hi> are only brought into the <hi>Houſe</hi> at the <hi>beginning</hi> of a Seſſion, and then dropt or loſt, it will not only be fruitleſs, but pernicious to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: For ſuch pretermiſſion, or connivance, will moſt certainly be interpreted into a Licenſe or Authority to commit them, and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, inſtead of being reſtrain'd, will be embolden'd to act yet more outragious Villanies, in hopes of the ſame impunity. And therefore my humble requeſt is, that, in Juſtice to your ſelves, and in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to the whole Nation, you will purſue our Grievances till they are redreſs'd in all Points, that is till the remedies for our future ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity are ripen'd into ſuch proviſionary Laws, as ſhall ſeem agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Wiſdom of your honourable Houſe. I am in all reſpects,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
